Finding Aid for the Rancho San Pedro: documents, [1854?]
UCLA Library Special Collections
Rancho San Pedro: documents
[1854?]
170/041
Rancho San Pedro
220 leaves: paper; 28 x 22 cm
Typescript abstract of title for the Rancho San Pedro, consisting of copies of documents related to the property, dated 1805 to 1854.
University of California, Los Angeles. Library Special Collections. Los Angeles, California 90095-1575
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
COLLECTION STORED OFF-SITE AT SRLF: Open for research. Advance notice required for access. Contact the UCLA Library Special Collections Reference Desk for paging information.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 4230403
Biography/History
The Rancho San Pedro, also known as the Dominguez Ranch, consisted of 75,000 acres gifted to Juan Jose Dominguez, a Spanish soldier, in 1784. In 1826, Dominguez's nephew, Manuel Dominguez, built an adobe home on the property for his family. Manuel Dominguez and his wife, Maria Engracia Cota, had ten children; six daughters survived, and were all raised in the adobe. The Rancho San Pedro was strategically located during the Mexican War and was the site of major skirmishes; it was also an important stagecoach stop for travelers, conveniently situated between the Pueblo of Los Angeles and the port of San Pedro.
Don Manuel Dominguez held public office under both the Mexican and U.S. governments in California. Before 1857, he was elected three times as Acalde (Mayor) and Judge of Los Angeles; he later served as a Supervisor for Los Angeles County. He was also selected as a delegate to the convention in Monterey which drew up the first State Constitution.
Scope and Content
Typescript copies of legal documents relating to Rancho San Pedro, including wills, complaints, orders from Governor Arrillaga, boundary reports, letters concerning territory, deeds, agreements, petitions, and decrees from the Board of Land Commissioners. The abstract was compiled by the firm of Grove and Wilkinson, probably for the purpose of proving ownership by Juan Jose Dominguez, and later, his nephew, Manuel Dominguez, to the Board of Land Commissioners. Includes index.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Genres and Forms of Material
Manuscripts.
Related Material
Bound Manuscripts Collection (Collection 170). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library.
Container List
Layout: Average of 22 lines per page.
Script: Typescript.
Binding: Beige buckram binding with spine title stamped in gilt.
- Contents (from index):
  - ff. 1-17: Statement of Stephen C. Foster
  - ff. 18-50: Statement by C.C. Grove in the abstract, early records, and archives, also a complaint made in 1805 concerning the cattle of Rancho San Pedro, Juan Jose Dominguez, and Manuel Nieto
  - ff. 51-58: Affidavit of Manuel Dominguez, May 25, 1854 concerning the origin of the complaint
  - ff. 59-63: Will of Juan Jose Dominguez, January 21, 1809
  - ff. 64-65: Order of Governor Arrillaga, Oct. 31, 1811; Complaint of Cristobal Dominguez, Dec. 2, 1822
  - ff. 66-69: Pablo Vicente de Sola document, Dec. 31, 1822
  - ff. 70-74: Will of Cristobal Dominguez, Jan. 5, 1825
  - ff. 75-79: Complaint of Manuel Dominguez, May 16, 1826
  - ff. 80-97: Transcript of Case No. 446 relating to Palos Verdes
  - ff. 98-100: Report of Jose Antonio Carillo in boundary dispute concerning Rancho San Pedro and Rancho Santa Gertrudis, June 26, 1828
  - ff. 101-102: Letter of Jose Antonio Carillo, June 26, 1828
  - ff. 103-104: Document dated July 7, 1828 addressed to the alcalde of Los Angeles relating to the border dispute
  - ff. 105-108: Report by Jose Antonio Carillo, July 10, 1828
  - ff. 109-110: Document addressed to the alcalde of Los Angeles, Aug. 1, 1828
  - ff. 111-115: Papers concerning suit in 1930[sic] by Manuel Dominguez against Antonio Ygnacio Avilla [sic] and Manuel Gutierrez
  - ff. 116-120: 1833, San Pedro Ranch documents
  - ff. 121-124: Deed and agreement between Manuel Dominguez and Nasario Dominguez, Sept. 25, 1833
  - ff. 125-130: Will of Marie de los Reyes Ybanes
  - ff. 131-145: Transcript of arbitrations settlement between Manuel Dominguez and Nicholas Gutierrez, 1834-1835
  - ff. 146-148: Agreement between Manuel Dominguez and Nasario Dominguez, June 30, 1835, Petition of N.M. Pryor
  - ff. 149-153: Report of special committee concerning Rancho San Pedro and Rancho of Suanga
  - ff. 154-155: Certification of the Pryor documents
  - ff. 156-158: Claims of Miguel Pryor to Suanga
  - ff. 159-160: Document concerning Manuel Dominguez and Rancho San Pedro
  - ff. 161-167: Transcript of 1840-1841 concerning the transfer of land from Rancho San Pedro to Rancho Los Palos Verdes
  - ff. 168-170: A document signed by Ygnacio Maria Alvarado, April 26, 1841
  - ff. 171-175: Agreement between Pedro Dominguez and Juan Temple, March 6, 1849
  - ff. 176-180: Deed from Pedro Dominguez to Juan Temple, March 26, 1849
  - ff. 181-186: Deed from Pedro Dominguez to Jose Antonio Aguirre, Feb. 9, 1850
  - ff. 187-189: Deed from Maria Victoria Dominguez to Manuel Dominguez, July 1, 1850
  - ff. 190-193: Deed from Manuel Rocha to Manuel Dominguez, June 12, 1852
  - ff. 194-196: Papers of transactions between Manuel Rocha and Manuel Dominguez
  - ff. 197-201: Petition of Manuel Dominguez for land claims in California, Oct. 25, 1852
  - ff. 202-206: Petition of Manuel Dominguez for confirmation of San Pedro Ranch, Oct. 25, 1852
  - ff. 207-217: Opinion of Board of Land Commissioners
  - ff. 218-220: Decree of confirmation.